I have to share this with you guys this
this is I'm using qbp and I was skipped
a little bit two years
ago and now I love it so what is qbp
qbp takes care of the missing piece of
on Prem
kubernetes that deals with one a virtual
IP so that you can have multiple
nodes uh that all share the same entry
point the virtual IP which I'll show you
in a second and two it takes care of
what metal lb has traditionally done
which is it assigns a a an an IP address
a virtual IP address to any load
balancer in your system
automatically so if you're familiar with
mini Cube you'll probably know mini Cube
service and mini Cube tunnel where it
kind of does the same thing but not
really right so what I mean QBE viip
does multiple things but the thing
that's so great about it is it does all
of it at the ARP level or the bgp level
which is the low low level in the
networking which is kind of where you
want to do this kind of stuff so so in
the past people would use metal lb and
then they would use ha proxy and you
know keep Al live D and all that and you
can still do that but they're not nearly
as as good they're not nearly as cool um
as Li viip now qbp actually has a very
serious bug right now uh since 1.29
kubernetes um there they for security
reasons kubernetes broke out admin. uh
comp uh into and I'll show you all this
uh into uh super- admin.com I think it
is and and they took away all the
permissions so so all the instructions
about how to get QB there a huge issue
on it that's a huge threat on on the qvp
thing there's also a huge issue on the
cube spray uh which is one of the places
I learned about how to get around it uh
Cub spray actually has a fix for this uh
it doesn't look like there's any
intention from the from the qbp uh
creators to fix this any time soon uh
based on their response on the issue so
but the bottom line is that QB will not
work uh at all until you do this fix and
I'm just to summarize the fix the fix is
when you first set up the static pod for
qvp and you create the kubernetes
Manifest for it you need to add super
Dash admin in one specific place that
I'll show you not both of them and that
will allow qvp to work uh the change to
the Manifest file will automatically be
picked up by C cubet which will see the
change and reload it and then it will
work it will start to work and uh do
what you expect and then as soon as then
you can actually join your doing the
bootstrapping process you can join your
QBE VI you can join your Cube and stuff
using QBE ADM um and then after you've
done all of that um you need to go back
in and change it back to admin. comp uh
or whatever the other one was and and
actually change it back because it needs
to it needs the information in that file
to be correct and that information got
broken out into super admin and admin by
kubernetes 1.29 and greater I think
we're at 131 now so the the moral of the
story is it is a pain but it's worth it
because once you have it working you get
a virtual IP that you can then P pass
off uh so I'm going to actually show you
that so um I'm on a Mac right now and
I'm just I've got my you know my super
admin is been set to be my cubin pig uh
so that I can do everything without
having to authenticate it on myth in my
in my CL poer um and I'm going to show
you the um I'm going to show you the
code that I used for installing qvp uh
this is in my DOT files by the way RBX
robd files I yes I could have done with
an could have done a cub whatever I tend
to just make scripts to help me remember
things so this script is available for
you you can go look at it and understand
what it's doing um again this script is
at uh RBX Rob SL do and and it's under
install Ubuntu and you can go into there
and find it um so um as you can see this
actually is is wrong I need to do a c
get pull on that that's out of date
because I was I have a Bastion host for
Linux and I changed it on there I didn't
update my stuff okay so this is the one
all right so uh I don't know if you saw
but the one before this didn't have
Services enabled I didn't know if I
wanted to do it or not and then I tried
it instead of metal lb and I'm like
totally sold on it now so um so what are
we doing here so up here in this script
I'm setting the I'm I'm defining I'm
running out a 192 168 Network don't
judge me I just bued it up fast I only
have 255 hosts in the range which is
kind of annoying um you can actually set
up a cider range here uh uh we'll see
later that qbp allows uh a cider Global
or a range Global uh thankfully because
the cider glob The Cider Global for this
particular range 2011 to 254 is very odd
it's not at a at a block boundary and so
they do allow range Global this is all
in the documentation for QC qbp if you
want to read through it yourself uh
we'll get down here uh to this stuff a
little bit later so um but understanding
this script is going to be the key to
understanding how to set up qvp so um
here I'm grabbing the interface uh I'm
grabbing the default interface make
absolutely sure that you set up the
default interface if you're if you're
working with BMS and you have a virtual
Bridge or something like that that
should not be a problem but this is one
way to grab that that uh using JQ uh I I
am going to make an entire video about
the necessity of learning the syntax of
JQ and yq in
20124 um I now believe that they are
more important than
SQL uh if you are in operations or
devops um if you're going to call
yourself a yaml programmer which is what
people in that Arena kind of are then
you really need to learn this you can do
Transformations and all kinds of cool
things um so it's worth learning it and
by the way I'm going to make a whole
series of videos about it because I uh
know it but not as well as I would like
I think it's more important to know JQ
and yq than said or even regular
Expressions actually um you need all
that stuff so install static pods um so
here we go so so this is me grabbing the
latest URL uh this is a standard way to
grab a latest URL using um uh this is
actually wrong this should probably be
tag name yeah they changed that at one
point let me let me actually test
that yeah let's do that Let's
do let's do um let's make it into a
function for the hell of it let's say uh
get uh let's see fetch latest
version let's put that code in a
different function because I want to
just call
that
two yeah okay latest version
um and then we can just Echo
that
Echo
version and then here we can have
version equals uh
fetch latest version it is a subshell
but it's kind of a faster subshell Shel
Che going to kill me on that shell
Che yeah Shel che's unhappy with a bunch
of stuff in here so I don't care I'll
come back and fix that
later this is funny this one this one it
wants me to do this yeah this is there's
actually a better way to do this that I
recently
discovered but I'm going to I'm going to
leave that in there for now the shell
check not passing is drivve me crazy
so version uh where's
version
verion wait do I have another one I I
declared version up here I guess I don't
need
it no version I just need VIP and
interface I also need range
Global uh I mean I like it when the
major things are up at the top
so VIP version version I guess I could
have fetched a version Echo if I wanted
to do that I could pass it as a global
after that but nah we'll actually pass
it and capture it that's easier it's
just
cleaner it's got problems I don't lie I
don't I'm not gonna lie it does have
problems but this is not my PR I look
just all right I'm getting distracted
there you go shall check passes um
anyway so let's actually mess with this
now we can go down here and turn off
this these other things for now and I
can turn on uh what is it
fetch uh latest version and we're going
to run that install
qvp there we go
um line nine it does not know what what
about what's
9 okay ipj route oh I'm not doing I'm
not on a Linux
machine yeah why is that
there I should put this in a function
too
no I should put this in a function say
uh get
um get default get latest
version get latest version get uh
default
interface and
then I mean h i can just I it's going to
print it right
out yeah that's it
um and this one I also don't need a set
version anymore yeah I can just print it
it'll just curl it'll just print it
right out yep so much
better all right so so so so so so so
yeah the tag name is the right one
that's why I did
this
yeah fetch going to fetch get latest
lastest
version all right get latest version
there we go
so uh let's actually test our other
thing
so uh get default interface
I should say like detect or assert or
something can I not
found oh wait what wait
what get default
interface oh I piece on
here that's why I broke it out anyway
that's not we're not on the Linux
machine so
uh that's that's about only
thing I do need that though later I I'm
I going to okay I'll put this on Bas and
we'll fix it okay wait where where do I
need the interface here we go so I need
the interface so version uh
interface equals uh get default version
no wait get default
interface get latest
[Music]
version yes that's what we want
um the rest can stay I don't need those
in there
[Music]
anymore all right let's Commit This and
I'll show you it on Bastion get
commit uh uh
Factor QV
stuff I have trans I have uh disposable
commits and this is my doile so I don't
care push
let me get on Bastion really quick am I
on Bastion here
nope Bastion let's go on
Bastion uh CD install one
to uh get
pull all right install
actually install key
VIP yeah I I just want to check I want
to test my IP thing
so get get uh default IP uh
interface I just have to test really
quick yay all right so that worked
um so let's go back to talking about
this this
script so setting up VIP VIP is uh a
it's a very cool thing that does stuff
that is going to be way over your head
but what it does is uses ARP and leader
election to
decide
um what I what who you know to to answer
the question about who is2
16612 200 so if you're running a proxmox
environment like I am you have three
control points you can't see them it's
kind of small but I have three control
points here and so anything that tries
to talk to these kubernetes components
needs to just have a single point of
access uh for the API and everything
else and that is the that is why we want
the virtual IP so normally to get this
you'd have to buy like uh you use H
proxy or you would buy you know a piece
of Hardware that would do it for you and
or you do round robin DNS which never
works right because if one of your
control planes goes down that means
onethird of your queries will fail all
of your stuff in your cluster so don't
do that even though there's a lot of
people who do that in production
including my team when I first got here
they're like oh well we just know that
one third are going to fail while we're
working on that one control P we don't
care that's a bad
idea especially since qpip exists um so
this is an IP that gets allocated gets
assigned um and and used and this is the
range so these are there's two functions
here I've already talked about there's
there's the the control plane endpoint
uh which is you know the IP the virtual
IP that that actually gets distributed
across all three just uh control ples
depending on one of they're up or down
and then there uh by the way you have to
have two up for it to work if you take
if you take I this is something I was
not expecting I was expecting there if
there was at least one up for it to
actually answer correctly but for some
reason qvp I I confirm this in testing
has to have at least two up so and I
there's extensive me video of me testing
that on live my live stream um I don't
know why that is but but that's the way
it is so if you have if you have only
have one control plan up uh qvp will
fail it will say this IP doesn't exist
and everybody will get you know your
your services is down because it
essentially says no your cluster is down
your cluster is not stable enough to
answer anything right now so but if you
get two up if you get at least two two
of those control planes up it will say
yeah I'm here great and it'll assume
it's up three of course same thing um so
what that means is if you're running
with three some people in a really large
un Prem environment will have like maybe
even up to five control planes um and
you you always want uh odd by the way I
don't know why that's why I Knows Why
with two it shouldn't that's not to get
leader election but whatever so and then
the second functionality is to like set
up these these IPS these virtual IPS to
automatically assign to anything with a
load balancer service and that is the
function that metal OB has provided in
the past but and the reason this is so
much better is because um if anything if
if if if the thing that's running your
load balance or service goes
down uh a new service will get started
up and a new uh load balancer entry
point will be created automatically
metal lb does not do that so that is
super cool if there's no other reason to
even consider this that is the reason
that that high availability of your uh
virtual IPS that are assigned to your
load balance you know um it's not a full
Ingress but it's you know it's that
metal lb part of it that you need um for
a home lab like mine I actually don't
need much more of an Ingress than that
because I just I can go as long as that
IP is is is consistent I can go to that
IP to do my testing and stuff and if I
wanted to sign an I if I wanted to
assign a domain name to it I could I
don't have to have all the other stuff I
don't have to have the other Ingress
stuff to go with it um because most of
my services are going to have their own
load balancer uh service and I just need
that to to show up on my local network
as an IP a virtual IP address and I can
just go to it and use it um for for for
a for a sort of a home lab environment
there's lots of things that that are not
included in that conversation like you
know like like uh but I'm not going to
get pulled into an ISO rabbit hole about
other things in ISO that are provided um
I really love the fact that I can assign
a single IP or a single thing to a
specific service and have it look like
it's its own server on my network it
that is amazing that's exactly the same
as I was running as a service uh you
know like a system D service or
something which I really love I really
love it because everything else is old
is very OG it's like oh hey you know
I've got a make do here I've got a a
cluster over here I got this application
here and I can just assign if I want to
I can assign my own host IDs or I or or
or domain name stuff externally uh that
resolve U that resolve to that IP
address and know that IP is never going
to change because um that load balancer
is going to get reassigned and I'm
pretty sure it gets reassigned the same
IP I'm pretty sure but I haven't
confirmed that I might if any if you
know put that in the comment I'm pretty
sure it always gets the same
IP but I could be dead wrong on that
honestly actually I could be totally
wrong on that I could be totally wrong
thank you for the fall um I don't know
that's actually something I got to find
out now because that would that would
defeat the whole argument I just said if
if the if the IP number is getting
changed
automatically to some other IP
address I I have to figure that out I
I'll report back I'll do another video
on that and find out for you I I I want
to believe that once an IP address has
been assigned to a given load balancer
service that that same IP is always
going to be associated with that load
balancer but I don't know that including
what if that service goes away and it
gets reimaged it's not it's not going to
reassign another IP we want that IP to
be to be consistent but I absolutely
don't know that this is the first time
I've ever used a qvp or this kind of
thing so I will I will find that out and
report back um but again for what I need
even if it did change the IP I would
just look up what it was you can specify
which public IP you're one to use when
you create a new balance or service can
you
really that which public IP to use you
can is that do you do that do you do
that in the service or in the qvp
thing so you can actually request anyway
if you know that if you know about that
let me know um so anyway this that's
what this is doing we're grabbing the
latest version uh this is here here's
how you install the static pod uh
remember to D- Services needs to be up
if you want Services um so I run this on
the control plane control plane one
first and uh this sets up a static a
static pod which is a reminder is a pod
that runs and and has a manifest file
that lives only on the endpoint uh on
the Node so this is not managed by
kubernetes it's kind of hard static pods
are kind of their own video static pods
run on the uh on the Node and for that
reason people don't like them uh the
cubet is a static
pod everything else you go go on the
thing you go look at all your your
static pods understanding static pods is
really essential um the main thing to
take away from this is you have to you
have to be able to connect to the node
and change uh the static pod
information um from you know through
through SSH you need to go over there
and and actually mess with this file
outside of kubernetes in order to change
things you can I found out turn off and
start up you can start off and you can
make change to the Manifest and restart
all you have to do is make change to the
Manifest and it will automatically be
seen as a new thing so um so that's a
that's really cool um and one of the
changes you do need to make is is
actually called out here Echo warning if
this is your first control plane change
change last admin. comp to Super admin
comp otherwise it won't work you can go
there's a link to the issue there you
can go read about why that doesn't work
and for a lot of people this is a reason
not use qvp for this kind of thing and
they want to use ha proxy that's up to
you I think it's still fine to do that I
I was about to throw it away if you
watched the live stream I was going off
on how stupid qbp is uh but I've since
kind of calm down and I'm okay with it
so um so that that gets you your stuff
and then your join your join command
which I can kind of Jump Ahead here uh
the Run QB ADM so this is this is how I
run my QB ADM uh oh wow that's not that
is yeah no that's it yeah this is my
qadm um and control plane yeah so
control Point endpoint uh pod slider I
actually think I'm probably going to
remove that I don't think that is
correct and then upload Zs I found out
you need to have that if you want your
Sears to be pulled down otherwise your
workers won't be able to join this is a
new thing I don't know when that start
started but you have to have that and
then the searchs are available for 2
hours uh before they're removed and then
you have to do upload searchs again it's
a relatively new thing um but anyway so
so yeah uh pinch the terminal I don't
know what that means make it
bigger you want me to make it bigger I
can I can go like
this is that what you
wanted so you can see it bigger
yeah you guys are probably on phones or
something let me go through and show you
all this stuff
again um all right
so so here we go we've got cider Network
1098 and then 192 so this is this is
mybm and it uh it's pretty basic I do
not use a config file um I there's
arguments to do it there arguments not
to do it so but let's go back to the
inst
VIP um to see
uh and then here's range. Global okay so
so uh I do not use celium uhuh I'm not
going to use celium I'm I'm not using
celium anymore I I compared celium to
Calico and that's a separate video uh I
think uh Calico still destroys celium um
there's no way I would ever use
after done after having done a pretty
exhaustive comparison of the two that's
a separate video uh sufficed to say
Calico has e has
bgp uh
and and all on tals I don't use Talis I
never will I think it's a bad idea even
though I was featured on their homepage
for saying how awesome it was I think
it's a horrible idea I don't think
anybody should use it um there you got
my answer on that how the hell are you
going to log into the system and set up
static pods on TS guess what you can't
all right so so here here's the static
pod um or how are you going to manage
your container engine you can't you have
to trust the tals creators to do
everything the right way because you
don't have SSH access to the nodes I I
think it's a I think it's a disastrously
bad model based on reality um and
there's a lot of people that just
significantly disagree that have a lot
more experience than I do but I would
never ever do it knowing what I know now
so um anyway you can set up this
interface this address control plane the
services here uh and then leader
election so don't remember to go in and
change your your VIP change it so what
does that look like let's actually go in
and look at a control plane uh s Sage
control Kate's control
one um we'll go to case control one.
local should be
up um all right so uh sudu VI Etsy
gretes um manifest so there's so there's
the super admin.com you see that there
there's admin.com and there's super
admin.com and that's a relatively new
thing kubernetes 1.29 and that actually
broke qbp when they did it so uh and you
can read it read that thread that I
listed if you want to know all the ways
that it broke it but it's easily fixed
if you're using Cube spray it's already
fixed in Cube spray they resolved it
they've created their recipes to do the
right thing uh next clusters after this
will be all Cube Cube spray clusters
from now on in my home lab because
they're just so much easier to manage
and all right so see this this this line
here uh this host path volume is set to
admin now when you first start this
you're going to get an error that'll say
uh basically I don't have sert access
and and how would you even see the error
you'd have to go to see the error at all
you'd have to do CD tail uh bar log you
can't you got to go here because there's
no kubernetes for this right you can't
there's I don't think you can even see I
don't think you can uh because it's it
hasn't you're you haven't bootstrapped a
cluster yet so there's no way to check
it so you have to actually go look at
the cube the logs
um for this thing this is actually super
annoying uh because you have to be root
so tail of our log pods and you go look
for the cube Cil so these all of this
static this is the only way to get any
debugging information on a static POD at
all uh because this is where this stuff
gets written uh this is one of the
reasons I was complaining about this
originally these are old errors these
are errors are now gone they're dated
108 10 yeah these are like these are
like yesterday's errors when I was
messing around so um and you'll see
these panic these panic app I was like
really harsh on the qvp project for
dumping
panics uh it does kind of annoy me um
however when once you have uh once you
do have a kubernetes cluster I'm pretty
sure you can just describe the pod which
is what I
did uh let me go do that here so K to
[Music]
uh uh pod
DN Cube
system uh Cube
VIP and is it VIP yeah VIP zero these
are they they only have the single
numbers on them
because uh because they're static pods
they look like Damon sets but they're
not you can actually deploy as a Damon
set but then you don't get the the
virtual IP for bootstrapping
um because you have to have a cluster to
see Dam said so so there um so there
there is you know all the configuration
of the pot so you can actually once you
have a cluster up so if you're like
debugging load balancer functionality
you can kind of do that um on here so
you can see here it has the path is
admin uh and it's using host path and
the different mounts make sure you don't
change the other Mount point in the in
the in the the file um because you'll
stop working if you do that I did that
and learned a highway so so let me show
you again so VI Etsy Bret
manifest uh Cube vip. yl I changed I I
did a said or no I did a pearl dasp and
and I I changed this one to Super adment
as well as this one and it
broke so you only want to change
this one to Super
admin and that will fix it enough to get
you bootstrapped but once and by the way
you have to do that for all of the
control planes when you bring them up
that that's not specified in the issue
it actually says it's only for the first
it's actually for all of them you need
to do it once with super admin to
bootstrap to to get the the control
plane to join and then it will have
other issues and so after that is done
you come back in here and you remove
this super and save it and then that
will cause cuet to reload it
automatically uh and at that point
you'll have a cluster up so you should
be able to do uh
describe um remotely if you want to see
what's going on rather than logging in
and looking at the logs which is pain in
the butt so that will actually give you
uh an error of something like that's
going on that that's not happy so this I
feel like this has been kind of a long-
winded explanation of qvp
uh hopefully I've said enough things to
uh convince you to kind of give it a try
and look at it um if you have any
questions at all about it please let me
know uh you can come in my chat you can
come in to our
Discord um and hey look and if you want
to you can also uh you know you can go
through those do files um I very
recently went through all of this with
qvp so I'm making this video for myself
as much as anybody else to remember what
I did to get it to work so
super pleased with qbp so far I mean
obviously there's a bug there uh that
needs to be fixed uh but if you're Cube
spray user you're not even going to
notice that um and um and if you're not
you can you can do the little trick that
I mentioned uh to get around that so I
wanted to put that out there give qvp a
look um and uh let me know let me know
how it goes for you